<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    <title>Hidden Elephants Blog</title>
    <link rel="self" href="https://hiddenelephants.co.uk/Blog/index.xml"/>
    <updated>2023-04-19T21:01:06Z</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Tim Taylor</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://hiddenelephants.co.uk/Blog/</id>

    <entry>
        <title>On Indentation in R</title>
        <link href="https://www.hiddenelephants.co.uk/Blog/on-indentation-in-R.html" />
        <id>https://www.hiddenelephants.co.uk/Blog/on-indentation-in-R.html</id>
        <updated>2023-04-18T21:57:58Z</updated>
        <content type="html">
            &lt;h1&gt;On Indentation in R&lt;/h1&gt;
            &lt;h2&gt;A Small Plea 🙏&lt;/h2&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Coding style, like many other things in life, is highly
            subjective. What one individual likes can feel like chilli in the
            eyes for another. Such is life and it's important not to get hung
            up on these things. That said, I'd like to make a small plea to a
            subset of the R community: &lt;em&gt;If you use 2 spaces for indentation,
            please please please trial using 4 or more spaces for your next
            piece of work&lt;/em&gt;. You may prefer it and there's no harm done if
            not.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;h2&gt;Why?&lt;/h2&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Until relatively recently (1 or 2 years at a guess) I followed
            the tidyverse &lt;a href="https://style.tidyverse.org/"&gt;style
            guide&lt;/a&gt; (or more likely just kept the RStudio default settings)
            and used 2 spaces for indentation of my code. Whether it was due to
            my eyes getting poorer or simply spending more time working with
            other languages, I came to realise that it was hard to quickly
            parse R code with this little indentation. After trialling 4
            spaces, and apologies in advance for the cliché, it was like a fog
            had lifted! My own code now feels less bunched up and easier to
            skim through. Similarly, when looking at others' codebases, I find
            it much easier to grok and orientate myself when they utilise more
            indentation.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;h3&gt;It’s not just me&lt;/h3&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Whilst a muggle from the UK is unlikely to sway too many
            opinions, I’m not alone in thinking more spacing is better. The
            &lt;a href=
            "https://cran.r-project.org/doc/manuals/R-ints.html#R-coding-standards"&gt;
            coding standards&lt;/a&gt; of the R project itself say:&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;blockquote&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The R Core Team recommends to use a basic indentation of 4 for R
            and C (and most likely also Perl) code …&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/blockquote&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Roger Peng, who advocates for 8 spaces, &lt;a href=
            "https://simplystatistics.org/posts/2018-07-27-why-i-indent-my-code-8-spaces/"&gt;
            wrote&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;blockquote&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Personally, I’ve found 8 spaces is good for my aging eyes. I
            think my rule is that the appropriate number of spaces of
            indentation is proportional to the square of my age (I’m still
            working on that model though). At this point, code with a 2 space
            indent is indistinguishable from flush left.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/blockquote&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Linus Torvalds, in relation to C, &lt;a href=
            "https://public-inbox.org/git/alpine.LFD.0.999.0710161722320.26902@woody.linux-foundation.org/"&gt;
            said&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;blockquote&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;In particular, a two-character indent (which hopefully nobody
            uses, but people are crazy) will be totally unreadable as a patch
            if you have the (fairly common, at least in UNIX projects) style of
            using spaces for less-than-eight-character-indents and tabs for the
            full 8 characters.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/blockquote&gt;
            &lt;h2&gt;A final thought&lt;/h2&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Whilst I hope that a few people read this and subsequently
            change their setup, the reality is that defaults matter and RStudio
            defaults to 2 spaces for indentation. Unless one of their
            developers feels inclined to slip in a cheeky change,🙈 🙏, I suspect
            my eyes will continue to be tested!&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>

</feed>